Pathway forward, what beckons? That's what
you have to ask yourself. And that's a
spiritual
journey. It's like, you have to start from
a perspective of humility, meaning you
don't know
who you are, seriously. Just like you
don't know who anyone else is, you really
don't. And so you
have to listen, and you have to investigate,
and you have to negotiate. It's like,
well, what would
make you satisfied? Do you want to be
satisfied? Are you a person who wants to be
satisfied?
There's a question. That's a hard one.
The cliched answer is obviously, the real
answer is
seldomly, right? You have to orient
yourself quite carefully to actually
prioritize your own
higher order harmony and satisfaction.
You have to be willing to subjugate
virtually everything to
that.
So, are you easy to get along with for
yourself? Probably not. That's the first
question of
conscience. Would you accept peace and
abundance if it came your way? And the answer
to that is,
probably not. And that's worth some
investigation, and to see what the obstacles in
the pathway are,
right? How are you your
own stumbling block? When
Adam is thrown from the
garden after the fall,
he's cursed to toil. Work
Life becomes work, and work becomes
toil. And when does work become toil?
How about when you're pursuing the wrong
thing? How about you're pursuing the wrong
thing for the wrong reasons? How about you're
pursuing the wrong thing for the wrong
reasons because you're a prideful usurper
who has violated the moral order?
How about that? That's how history begins
in the biblical text. That's literally the
fall into history.
Prideful pursuit of
burdensome aim. Right, so
then, you negotiate with yourself and think,
what would satisfy a creature like me,
actually, if I admitted what I wanted,
if I allowed myself to understand
what actually impedes me if I
looked at my reality instead of my
self delusion.
Right, just like trying to negotiate
with someone you love. A marriage,
a very close relationship. What do
you want? Well, you have to listen.
Just like you have
to listen to yourself. You have to see where
you're prompted. How are you prompted?
By
enthusiasm. That's calling by negative
emotion, by anxiety, by pain. That's
conscience. Conscience
tells you when you're not on the optimal
pathway forward and calling invites you
forward or
transforms your aim. Right. So those
are two manifestations of the divine,
historically
speaking. Right. That's the pillar of
light in the darkness and the pillar of
darkness
at night that guide the lost Israelites
through the chaos in the desert forward to
the promised
land. Right. Conscience, the voice of
negative emotion. Calling, the voice of
positive emotion.
If you listen, they align you.
Right. But you have to
listen. Pathways forward. An
unimpeded pathway forward
produces positive
emotion. Although that's complicated by the
other factor we described, which is you
don't want too
easy a route. Why? Because it doesn't compel
development. So think about it. Think
about a
child playing one -on -one
basketball. Who does he want for
an opponent? Someone who never scores a
basket or someone who's as good as him
that puts him on the edge of development,
challenges him,
or maybe someone who's slightly better so
that he really has to work to win and can
imitate to
improve his skill. So if you're looking
for a pathway forward, you want one that's
optimally
tilted upward so that the pathway not only
gives you some reasonable probability
of attaining the
goal, but compels your development along
the way. If you're a good mentor, that's
the sort of goals that
you set people. Right.
So if I set you a goal that's trivial, you're
going to feel insulted first because I
have no
faith in your developmental capacity and
underestimate you. But there'll also be no
challenge in it. And that challenge, that
meaning, it's not merely a matter of
positive emotion
because you want some. Imagine you make
a rat hungry and you train it to run
down a runway to
get a piece of cheese. It's motivated
by the knowledge of the goal to run
forward. Now,
imagine you take the same rat.
And you put it in its enclosure
and the goal is in front of
it. And you use a ventilation system
to introduce some cat odor. That rat makes
a beeline down the runway much faster.
And so you
might ask, well, how would you put yourself
in a situation of optimal motivation?
You could be
running towards something extremely
valuable and you could be running away from
something extremely terrible.
Right. And then that's a metaphysical
landscape. Right. Because that's the
metaphysical landscape
of the abyss and the and the stellar or
hell and heaven. Right. Do you
want to be running away from
something terrible towards something good?
Right. Optimally motivating. So pathways,
tools. So when
we see the world, we don't
see objects. We see.
Pathways. And we see objects of relevance.
And the positive objects of relevance are
tools. A chair.
Is a chair an object? Is a stump a chair?
If it's at the right height? Well, the
answer to that is,
can you sit on it? Is a beanbag a chair?
If you can sit in it, on it. Do they share
any features in
common except relative size? Pretty much
no. They're defined by their functional
utility.
Right. So the things we see in the world,
we don't see. Right. So the things we see
in the world,
are defined by their functional utility. I
mean, the objects. We don't see objects.
We see tools.
We see pathways. We see obstacles. Tools.
Positive emotion. Obstacles.
Negative emotion. Pathways.
Depends on their gradient and their
complexity. Pathways, tools, obstacles.
There are social
tools. Friends and allies.
So you can think about the
material world. Tools and obstacles. You
can think about the social world. Friends
and foes.
Right. Same notion. What's a friend? A
compatriot. Someone that you can walk down
the same path with.
Someone you can be of mutual aid to. Someone
who shares your frame of reference and
your goals.
Someone who's playing the same game with
you. If they're a good friend, you can play
multiple
games. That's how a child establishes a
friendship. They play once. The game goes
well. They make another date for
play. If the recurrent play.
Is productive and develops them
they have a friend right right
a friend is a tool for the
acquisition of proximal goals but also
a compatriot in the adventure and a
means of
transformation across time if
that's a good friend right
foes well they're in your way
pathways tools obstacles
friends foes agents
of magical transformation
that's fun what's an agent
of magical transformation how
is there magic in fiction when
you're playing a game you're playing
by a set of rules that's what defines
the game you could think about those as
principles they're
not exactly borders or boundaries or
restrictions they're enabling principles right
when you're
playing basketball you can't play chess
and you might think about that as a
limitation
but the rules of the game which are enabling
principles allow the game to exist so
to think
about rules as impediments is foolish
although they have their boundaries the rules
are actually
enabling principles you can conduct yourself
radically different on the perceptual
emotional
attentional and action front by conducting
yourself according to different sets of
principles you can conduct yourself
according to different sets of principles
you can conduct yourself according to
different sets of principles and then you can
imagine that
there are terrible games that no one wants
to play there are games that degenerate
when you play them
they're games that people enjoy there are
games that improve as people in play them
and enjoy and
there are games that improve as people play
them and enjoy and incorporate more and
more people
right that's a very good game now imagine
that those games are sequenced in a
hierarchy of value
poor games at the bottom great
games at the top and that's
right that's a very good game now imagine
that those games are sequenced in a
hierarchy of value
and as you become a more accustomed
accomplished and wise player you play a better
and better game
imagine someone who's a good sport who's
a great athlete imagine someone who's a
great athlete in
a poor sport first okay so at one level
they're playing the game properly right
they've mastered
the skills they this is very common in
athletic it's like the basis of virtually
every sports
movie you know some kid who's a hot shot
who's mastered the basics of the game and
who is perhaps
heads and head and shoulders above the rest
of his team in terms of his raw ability
and but he's
terrible and what does terrible mean he it's
everything's about him except blame and
the blame
is about everybody else and does he do
anything to facilitate the growth of his
teammates no he just
complains and carps when they either don't
appreciate his stellar qualities or fail
to deliver on command and the
wise coach comes along and says
you're pretty damn talented but you have
a lot to learn right and then as the plot
progresses you
see the narcissistic but highly skilled
young person relies often through a
sequence of painful
encounters those would be self -imposed
obstacles that there are higher order games
than mere
victory in the moment and also in so also
than selfish self -aggrandizement no
matter the level
of talent that's a plot obviously a plot
with character development but it's a plot
with character
development that's a feel -good movie
well why because we like to see people
transform upward
right because implicitly if not explicitly
we believe that that's possible and we
hope to the
degree that we care for ourselves and for
others that that pathway exists and that
we could walk
it and we go to that movie and we watch
so that we can imitate it and learn right
and so the skill is
important so that that might mean that if
you think about the hierarchy of games
like the simplest
level would be mere knowledge of the rules
and then increasingly expert application
of those rules
until you're an expert player within the
confines of a single game but then there's
a tournament of
games right and then there's a tournament
of games where you have to develop your
teammates
and then there's a tournament of games where
you have to develop your teammates in a
manner that
generalizes to other games and then there's
the set of all those other games that
you could generalize from that
you could apply to your life
right that's a hierarchy that's jacob's
ladder right so if you're playing that
highest order
game where you play every game you play you
play in a skilled manner as a good sport
such that
you facilitate the development of yourself
and people around you such that people
notice and
your reputation grows and you're invited
to play a never-ending sequence of games
that's what you want for your
child and that's why you
tell them it doesn't matter whether
you win or lose even though it does
it matters how you play the game well why
because the game isn't the game the game
is the metagame and you don't support nate
the meta game to the game that's part of
the divine
order you don't invert that right because
it makes you shallow and weak and prideful
and a usurper and that's a bad idea
what's an agent of magical transformation
someone had to Johanna might have been
up to slam all that had to go in for him
that's the thing
who resets your aim right so you're
you're in this game that's your world the
principles that you
abide by but you're it's narrowing you
you're you've exhausted it as a place of
potential and
maybe you know that because your your soul
aches the enthusiasm is gone right the
horizons are no
longer wide enough and someone comes along
and says there's a better game afoot well
that's what
happens in the lord of the rings that's
what happens in the hobbit to bilbo bilbo
first frodo's in the lord of the rings i
believe bilbo in the hobbit bilbo he's like
pinocchio he's a
little guy in an ordinary place that's
the shire right it's bounded it's a good
place but it's very
isolated there are great things going on
in the outside world great battles of good
and evil but the shire is protected it's
protected by the way by these striders
aragorn is one of them striders are
camouflaged descendants of ancient kings who
attend the
boundaries unbeknownst to the inhabitants
within the keepers of the tradition and
the principles that all that naive stability
depends on outside the realm of the
boundary guardians is the
realm of the battle of good and
evil and gandalf shows up to
invite
the
hobbit to transform oddly he becomes
a thief first right well why
because he's too
nietzsche said most of what people regard
as morality is their own cowardice
right there's
a big difference between being too afraid
to break the rules and being too good to
break the rules
and if you're too afraid to break the
rules the best way to maintain any self
-regarding
guard is to classify yourself as too good
to break the rules highly improbable so
when the hobbit
transforms he transforms down in a way
first he breaks the frame of morality that
defines his
current state of being or his game he
expands his purview of accessible skills
he incorporates from
the union perspective he incorporates
shadow elements you want your aggression on
your side
right you don't want to sequester it off
you don't want to sequester it off you
don't want to
repress it in isolation you don't want to
repress it in the freudian sense you want
to bring it on
board and put it in its place that's what
adam is called upon by god to do name and
sub do
everything in its proper place right sexuality
in its proper place aggression in its
proper place
rage in its proper place everything in its
proper place in relationship to well to
what well that's
what gandalf shows up to do in his proper
place to do everything in its proper place
in relationship to
well to what well that's what gandalf
shows up to do in his proper place to do
everything in its proper place
that's what gandalf points out right now
remember the battle there is dragon and
treasure that's the
oldest that's really the oldest human story
the dragon treasure narrative we'll see
why it's because
there's opportunity where there's ever
wherever there's challenge there's
opportunity wherever
there's danger and you can take the stance
of a prey animal and freeze which is
what the victims
of the animal of the animal of the animal
of the animal
basilisk do in the second volume of the
harry potter story remember there's a great
serpent that
lives underneath the magic castle and
if you gaze upon it then you freeze why
because that's what a
rabbit does when it sees a wolf and what
does the hero do break some rules to face
the dragon in its
lair to transform in the phoenix story
it's the phoenix that comes along after
harry's wounded
and revitalizes him and he's going to be a
hero and he's going to be a hero and he's
going to be a hero
as he frees jenny the dragon hoards
virgins and gold that's the age -old story
and the phoenix
dies and is reborn and is the avatar
of that spirit and that's a death and
resurrection story
and that's a consequence of one game
disintegrating and being replaced by another
and that pattern is the death and resurrection
pattern right things fall apart and
then they reconstitute things fall apart
and then they reconstitute hopefully they
reconstitute and then they
reconstitute at a higher and higher level
with each collapse well otherwise the
collapse can be
a spiral downward that's a trip
to dante's inferno there are
positive agents of transformation
the degree to which they're magical is
proportionate to the distance from your
current
game right so if they're higher order
agents of magical transformation you don't
understand them
at all and they might be
utterly terrifying because
their mode of transformation is not the
same as the mode of transformation of the
phoenix
the mode of world construal violates all
of your principles it's very difficult to
distinguish
between a savior and an enemy right because
of the degree of radical transformation
that's required
and so that's why all the hobbits in the
shire are and and bilbo too are terrified
of gandalf
right he's respected and admired but the
respectable people they're not so sure what
to do with them it's because they've
already pridefully defined the
structure of the world they're not afraid
of the intellect of the mind as it were
they're proud of the nature of the world
and so they're ashamed of it and the
only X who're allowed to speak simply as
the power of the mind is known to us that's
what keeps them
female versions and then there's downward
agents of magical transformation too and
those are you
could call them messengers of the abyss or
messengers of hell and they're they put
forward
a temptation to play a downward game and
there's no limit to the upward game because
it ascends
into the heavenly the ineffable and there's
no limit to the downward game because
hell is a
bottomless pit remember and you may remember
you may know story of jacob's ladder
jacob is a very
bad man in the biblical account he's a
reprobate he's too close to his mother he
betrays his
brother he betrays his father eventually
so badly that his brother determines to
kill him
jacob leaves and on on his way to
visit his uncle to start a new life
and on the way he
vows to do better and he builds an altar
aiming upward and he makes a sacrifice to
indicate that
he's willing to let go of the things that
are impediments to his progress and he
falls asleep
and he has a dream of a ladder cycling
upward that has angels descending upon it
from heaven to earth
with god at the pinnacle but not visible
right that's the ultimate upward aim
that recedes as
you move towards it and
that's the upward pathway to
the city of this heavenly city
on the hill that requires
diligent sacrifice or work
right uh dante's inferno that
story of a descent into hell is a
poetic representation of a journey through
the realms of experience defined by
misaligned aim
hierarchically sequenced
dante put satan at the core
of the inferno frozen in
place immovable consequence of
overweening pride surrounded by those who
betray the worst sin in dante's estimation
because betrayers invert love
right so agents of downward
transformation tempt
towards the abyss and there are magical
agents as well and they might offer power
or they might offer pleasure right and
that's also an insubordination because
if power is dominance and dominance is
associated with aggression it has its place
right integrated aggression makes you
implacable and immovable and and a force to be
reckoned with but
aggression serving power when power is
elevated to the highest place that makes you
what did what did lucifer say in paradise
lost better to rule over hell than to
serve in heaven yeah well the biggest
thing is that the devil in hell is the
worst loser right and so power games are a
very bad idea
and so but that's the temptation when
christ is tempted in the desert after his
baptism 40 days
in the desert the spirit of satan
comes to him with three temptations to
be given what he doesn't
deserve to be saved from what he does deserve
and to rule the world with power right
right all misaligned and inverted aims so
that's an agent of magical transformation
in the negative direction once you know
that that means
the reconfiguration of aim downward right
so the frame of reference shifts and
changes you play a
worse game right and so that's the landscape
of good and evil right sequence of
games you could
say stretching from hell to heaven right
and that's a ladder that i've seen people
douglas
murray you know douglas murray he's been
in many war zones now and has seen some
terrible
atrocities and his conclusion from that
was that since that there is great
evil in the world and
the inevitable conclusion that you draw
from understanding that there's great evil
in the
world is that the opposite of that obviously
exists at least insofar as whatever's
the greatest
good is as far away from that as you can
get right and so that's i suppose some
advantage to the encounter with the dragon
of evil right so it's a good example of
what is evil and that is the apparent
part of the idea of what is and the reason
that the answer is in its in its darker
forms is that
once you're convinced of the reality
of evil then you're alert to the
possibility of good
and maybe motivated to pursue it yeah
that's a form of harrowing of hell
i suppose back to the
frame what is and what
should be how we should
act that's a value frame
right how we should act well
Well, it's defined in relationship
to the aim, obviously.
Should is what moves you
forward towards the aim.
A bigger question on the value front
is, what then might the aim be?
And we'll answer that to some degree.
We have investigated that to some degree.
We'll answer it a bit in more detail now.
Okay, so let's take a look at
the structure of this frame.
We talked about tools, obstacles, friends,
foes, pathways, agents of magical
transformation.
Okay, so that's one way of looking
at it from a perceptual perspective.
That's what you see.
That's what you experience.
Let's look at it from an
emotional perspective.
Okay, so what is is insufficient.
It's got a neutral or negative tone.
You want to improve it.
It's at least defined as negative in
relationship to the destination, right?
There's a polarity there.
And that polarity is really what gives
you your impetus to move forward.
You want to optimize that polarity.
If you have a little kid, you
don't give them a task that,
they can't do, and you don't give
them one that's too easy, right?
You set the bar in the proper manner.
This is something you really want
to learn to do with yourself.
It's like, if you find
you're not doing something,
one thing you can do is set
the bar slightly lower, right?
Because you can play and see, okay,
here's the thing I'm planning to do,
but I'm not doing it.
What if I aim to doing half of it?
Then you can see, will I do it?
If the answer is no, well, try a quarter.
And maybe you'll see that you'll
get some forward movement.
And what that means is you've now
met yourself where you actually are.
Now, it may be that the aim is
wrong, and that's a different issue.
But I wouldn't draw that
conclusion immediately, right?
You might as well, if you set up a frame,
you might as well play within it and
see how you can adjust it in accordance
with what you need before making the
radical move of shifting the aim.
If you can't adjust the aim so
that you will move forward,
well, then you have to take the more
revolutionary move of reconfiguring the aim.
But this is an element
of behavioral therapy.
If you're trying to help someone progress,
you define the direction of
progression, usually dialectically.
What the hell do you want?
Okay, what do you think might be
a pathway out of this problem?
Now that maybe we've
conceptualized the problem.
Hypothetically, if you were playing,
what do you think might constitute some
improvement? So then you define it.
I say, well, go back for a week
and just try that out, right?
Here's some tasks.
You don't impose the tasks as the interlocutor,
as the investigator, you negotiate
them.
What about trying this?
Come back in a week and
tell me what happened.
You come back and you
say, well, that was easy.
I did it right away. It's like, great.
We probably didn't set the bar quite
high enough, but congratulations.
Or you come back and say, I did nothing.
It's like, okay, maybe we construed
the problem wrong or the solution.
But maybe you ask too much of yourself.
Well, it wasn't much.
I was going to clean up my mess.
I cleaned up my room.
I didn't do it.
Well, this is maybe someone who
hasn't done it for 15 years.
It's like, okay, organize a drawer, right?
See if you can do that.
If you can't do that,
organize half a drawer.
And usually what you'll see is
that in the Pinocchio movie,
when Pinocchio goes to the depths, he
encounters this whale monstro that lives
at the bottom of the abyss, and the first
time he sees the whale, he turns tail and
runs.
That's a very common mythological trope.
It's the flight of the hero.
At first sight of the chaos of the villain,
because the magnitude of the task is
greater than it appears, and Pinocchio
turns around, guided by his conscience,
and eventually determines to
face the fire breathing whale.
It's a fire breathing whale.
It's obviously a dragon
fire breathing whale.
And he goes into the depths and
finds his father and revivifies him.
He brings the tradition back to
life by going down into the depths.
When someone is. First about
to embark on a minor task,
but that minor task signifies a
transition from descent to ascent,
then it's a revolutionary
move, even if it's small.
And so if you're aiming up and that's new,
and you might take flight at the fact
that you've determined to aim up and the
weight that that places on you and find
that you're impeded even in your ability
to do something small
because it's not small.
Right. And I had clients who lived in their
high school bedroom until they were 45
and hadn't cleaned it up in 30 years,
and that's not a small problem.
And so even when we decided to turn
it around just ever so slightly,
the surface of the problem was let's make
some organization in your junk drawer.
But the essence of the problem is just how
much has your mother been doing for you
for the last 45 years and just exactly.
Why? And just exactly why
did you go along with that?
And what are you going to do about the
fact that that's four and a half decades?
Right. So that's what you're
confronting behind the facade of the.
I had a client who I was
introducing to an elevator.
She had agoraphobia.
Agoraphobics don't like elevators
because they're trapped.
And in their trap, they
can't get to a hospital.
And if they have a heart attack in the
elevator when they're trapped, then they die.
And if there's other people,
people in the elevator when they're trapped
while they're dying of a heart attack,
then they make a fool of
themselves while they die.
And that's shameful.
So the elevator isn't an elevator.
It's a place of confinement,
death and humiliation.
And when I had my client in front of the
elevator doors and they opened, she said,
that's a tomb.
And that was so interesting because you
could see the got a glimpse behind the veil.
It's like, why would you
be afraid of an elevator?
It's like you can die anywhere.
Right. And you can die a humiliating
death in panic anywhere.
And an elevator is as good a place as any.
And you don't know that when you're
going on to an elevator, you're bravely
confronting death.
But you would learn that if you
stopped being able to do it.
Right. And so then you teach the person
that even though that's what they think,
they can still move forward, then
they get a lot braver. Yeah.
So, okay, tools, obstacles,
friends, foes, pathways,
magical. Agents of transformation.
Let's abstract that a little
bit away from character.
What do you see in the world where
you are, where you're going?
What happens when you move forward?
You act. What are the possibilities?
Things you predict.
Okay. What does it mean to be
able to predict something?
It means that the way that you're perceiving
the world puts the world in alignment
with your aims.
Right. You go out, you start
your car and it starts great.
That's a predicted outcome.
Or maybe you go out and you start
your car and it grinds to a halt.
Maybe that or maybe you're driving on the
freeway and the car ceases to function on
a very busy highway.
And you're not that popular at work.
And one more late arrival with a half
-wit excuse, and that's the end of your
job. And it's a rat
trap of an old vehicle.
And you're like 35 and you're thinking,
what the hell is wrong with this car?
And that's a big question, because
why do you have that car exactly?
And why is it such a rattle trap?
And maybe you hate your job and it's
pretty damn convenient that the car has
breathed its last gasp.
And what's the problem with the car?
Well, that's another one of those situations
where the car is just the proximal
covering for a slew of problems.
Maybe if you had your act together,
you'd have a car that actually worked.
And maybe you're old enough
so that you should have one.
And then you're like, oh, well, that's
a problem. Then maybe you'd have a job.
Then maybe your wife
wouldn't have left you.
Maybe your kids would still see you.
Maybe you wouldn't be in hell regularly.
And that's what the hell
is wrong with your car.
And so that's that layered structure
that's underneath everything.
That's why so often when you're arguing
with someone you love, some trivial thing
will come up. And then
things explode around.
It's because that trivial thing is
an indicator of unplumbed depths
below the surface.
That go all the way down, often to a
betrayal and untangling that is one
brutal journey.
If you do it, you can redeem
the dead, so to speak.
You can revivify your relationship.
You can maybe solve the problem.
But it's definitely a trip downward
to the bottom, which is extremely
demanding.
And then with any luck and emergence
on more solid ground moving forward.
You have a predicted outcome.
Well, if you've laid out the plan, you
encounter the tools, the pathway forward,
and the tools that will move
you to your destination.
You're predicting that it's like
the definition of a good plan.
A good plan is one that gets you to
your destination in a predictable way.
Okay, you can encounter obstacles, and then
you can imagine obstacles of different
sorts. There's obstacles you understand.
Like, if I'm walking there, you're
in the way, that's pretty easy.
I just do this. I do that.
And I don't have to change my frame of
reference, except in a micro way, and I can
continue merrily on my path.
The gentleman we talked about earlier, whose
car breaks down on the side of the road
and who no longer has a job.
That's a lot bigger obstacle, right?
That's an unpredicted event, right?
And you can think about an unpredicted
event, like a radically unpredicted event as
a hole in your plan that you fall.
That's the rabbit hole that
Ellis falls down, right?
That's a rabbit hole. It's like.
Oh, there's some things that are going
on in the world that I didn't take into
account, and it's down
the rabbit hole we go.
And God only knows what we're
going to discover there.
Like the gentleman who has to figure out
why he's 35 and has a car that doesn't
work. It's like he could probably spend
a year thinking about that, right?
And rectifying what every single micro
decision he made in the last 30 years that
led him to that point.
And that's a dragon.
All those little biting.
Reptiles of past failures that aggregate
into a monster that comes flinging forth or
springing forth and devours.
That's an ancient story as well.
I'll tell you a story
like that as we progress.
What happens when you encounter
something unexpected?
Well, it sets you back.
It stops you in your tracks.
Why? Well, you have to
recalibrate your strategy, right?
That's a trivial problem.
Maybe you have to recalibrate your aim.
Whew. That means
everything's up in the air.
Maybe you have to recalibrate
your aim at a deep level.
That's even worse because the game you're
playing depends on other games, and it's
nested in even higher order games.
And maybe you're not
wrong in a trivial way.
That means you can just dance out of the
out of the oncoming traffic, let's say, but
that you really have to
reconfigure every bloody thing.
Not only that you experience emotionally
and conceptually, but even that you
perceive.
Right. So look out.
And this is also why people
fall prey to willful blindness.
You know, they don't want to look.
They don't want to look.
There are none so blind as
those who will not see.
Well, it's no wonder.
It's no wonder.
And the more you're willfully blind in the
face of the unexpected, the bigger the
monster you won't look at gets, right?
Brutal, brutal.
Then it comes leaping out at a moment's
notice when you're least prepared.
And that's the end of you.
Unpredicted outcome.
What happens emotionally?
If I see an obstacle, it's frustrating.
It produces negative emotion.
Produce anger can produce anxiety.
All those emotions, the
negative emotions all cluster.
Novelty also produces
negative emotion, right?
And it's proportionate.
The negative emotion novelty produces is
proportionate to the number of rule games
it violates, right?
So if it just blows up.
If it just blows the game into
bits, then it's terrifying.
If it violates one presupposition,
well, then it's less intimidating.
But it can be an anomaly, can be an
agent of magical transformation.
In fact, that's what an anomaly is,
a novelty, something unexpected.
It's an agent of magical transformation.
It's going to force you to change.
It's a dragon and a treasure
at the same time, right?
It's a dragon because who the
hell knows where you are?
You thought you were somewhere.
You're not there. And where are you?
You don't know.
Maybe you're somewhere better if you
could conduct yourself properly, right?
So it's reasonable to take stock.
That's a stumbling block, right?
I tripped over this.
Well, what is it?
It's an impediment.
Or is it a portal to somewhere new, right?
It can be either.
It can be both.
It produces a mix of emotions.
Fear freezes, but it
also elicits curiosity.
Now.
Those usually work depends on
the magnitude of the novelty.
As I said, if it's just a minor novelty,
mostly what it elicits is curiosity.
If it's a medium sized novelty,
then it freezes you first.
This is what an animal do is
freeze and then it waits.
Maybe it'll move its eyes
and maybe it'll sniff.
And it's detecting to see what implications
the unexpected thing happened.
And if nothing else happens, it'll
unfreeze and it'll start to explore.
Right. And so. And that means that the
emotion has turned from anxiety mediation to
dopaminergically mediated exploration.
And so that's a dragon
and a treasure, right?
In conjunction.
And so down the rabbit hole to explore.
That's the realm of the novel.
The novel.
This is so interesting.
The novel is everything you didn't
take into account in your game, right?
So you play a game and it defines a
little bit. A little world, right?
And as long as the game is going well,
you can stay within that little bounded
world. It's a walled garden,
that bounded world of the game.
But the world isn't a basketball game,
even if you're a professional basketball
player.
And the game, if you're a professional, the
game can be dominant enough so that you
make your living with it.
But there's a whole
world outside the game.
Now and then the world comes
crashing into the game.
That's the serpent in the
Garden of Eden, by the way.
That's the world come crashing
into everything that's bounded.
It's always there.
No gardens without serpents.
Why? Because you can't
exclude everything, right?
You lay out your game, you lay out your
perceptual frame, but all the things you
ignore, they're still there.
And now and then they come crashing through,
and then you have to take them into
account. And that can be a good
thing if it ups your game.
But it can be a cataclysmic thing,
especially if you're not prepared for it.
If you haven't practiced
it, you want to practice.
That's why it's so important for
children to practice losing.
You have to develop resilience.
You have to be able to take the punches.
You have to be able to roll with them and
keep going and persevere in the face of
obstacle and difficulty.
You have to explore because you want to
win the metagame, not just the game.
And you can lose 50 times and
then win, and you win, right?
That's the story of most entrepreneurs
who are hyper successful.
You know, many entrepreneurs, they fail
multiple times before they succeed.
And so you need that.
Yeah.
Ability to dance with what's novel
and to have faith in your ability
to persevere when something new comes
your way and to understand that there are
games outside the game that you're playing
and that this obstacle might be a portal
to a better game, especially if
you conducted yourself properly.
Now, part of that proper conduct
is voluntary exposure, right?
So this is what you do in behavior therapy
to people who have anxiety disorders.
You identify what they're
afraid of and avoid.
And you encourage them to adopt an
exploratory stance towards them.
And they become expert at the exploratory
stance, and that doesn't make them less
afraid. It makes them braver.
And so then they can prevail in the
face of their anxiety because now they
understand
that they're the thing that can face things
instead of the prey animal that has to
freeze or retreat.
Right? That's what you want your
kids to practice. That's right.
Do you want to have them on the edge of
disaster, so to speak, on the edge of chaos?
Always. That's where maximal play is.
Men understand that in particular.
Men play rough with little kids,
really, from the time they're babies.
Throw them in the air and bend
them around and flip them.
And the kids are enthralled by that.
They're desperate for that because they
want to be put on the edge, always.
That's the place of
maximally exciting play.
And that's a real place, right?
It's a phenomenological place.
And you know you're there because you're
engaged, and it's deeply engaging, and it's
playful, and you're improving.
And so, and maybe with that on your slate,
you look forward to the day, even if
you're not doing so well.
So, you can encounter a tool and an
obstacle and a friend and a foe.
And you can encounter something you don't
expect and can't define and can't even
really perceive.
What's going on here?
You know, this often happens in interpersonal
relationships where you're conducting
a conversation and something goes astray.
Right?
Very common occurrence in marriages where
there's a disjunction in communication.
And the outcome you expect as a consequence
of your utterance fails to make itself
manifest. It's like, what's going on here?
Did I say something? Did I make a mistake?
That's a good place to start.
It's like, was I misunderstood?
Or is there some fundamental disagreement
about first principles here?
Right? And you can skate over that.
Maybe you should if it only happens
once because what the hell.
But if it's a recurring pattern.
It's time to go down the rabbit hole
and adjust the axioms of the game.
And see if it can be reconstituted
so that that discontinuity vanishes.
That's a constitutional
crisis, you might say.
And a difficult thing to negotiate.
Down the rabbit hole.
That's what novelty looks like.
Right? It's half promise.
That's the treasure.
It's half threat.
Look the hell out.
And whether it's promise or threat
depends to a large degree on how you
conduct yourself.
Is fire useful or dangerous?
Well, it's useful and
dangerous like everything.
That's that weird perversity of
the so-called object, right?
It's a beer bottle is a
weapon in a bar fight, right?
Is it really a weapon?
It's like, well, once you're dead,
you can answer that question.
It might be more really a weapon than a
beer bottle in the right circumstances.
Depends on who's playing
what game, really.
And so, you know, every
object is different.
Every object has a distribution
of possibility around it, right?
So there's the object and then there's
the possibility of the object.
And that realm of possibility can
be explored in different games.
The beer bottle is a good example of that.
It's like smash.
Now it's a knife, right?
Is it really a knife?
It's like if death is the arbiter
of reality, then yes, it's a knife.
And so, so then, you know, one question
that arises is in the face of,
is there a.
Stable pattern that you can make
manifest in the face of the uncertain
that increases the probability
that you will prevail.
That's the religious question, right?
How do you deal with what's
unknown in the world?
How do you adjust yourself so that
you're maximally situated to improve
the game as you play it, right?
There's an element of courage in that.
There's an element of faith.
There's a tremendous amount of attention.
There's a tremendous amount
of intention, right?
There's practice.
There's wisdom, there's
guidance from tradition.
The novel, I think, is the biggest of the
anomalous, is the biggest of categorical
problems, right?
Because when you play a delimited game,
when you're looking at one thing,
there's an infinite number of things
you're not attending to, right?
When you're playing one game, there's a
never ending array of games you could be
playing. So there's a massive difference
between the landscape that you've
configured proximally
and every possibility.
And so it's the fact of that
unlimited landscape of possibility.
That's the cardinal issue of life.
And you could say that the determination of
how you encounter the radically unknown,
that's the most important skill, meta
skill that you could possibly learn.
That's what you're teaching your kids when
you're teaching them to be resilient and
to develop, right?
How do they stay on the edge
and prevail continually?
And that's that's a meta skill.
I would say again, that's
the religious meta skill.
Like the religious landscape is
the landscape of heaven and hell,
but it's also the landscape of
it's the landscape of possibility.
The water that the spirit of God hovers
upon at the beginning of time in the story
of Genesis is the landscape of possibility
that your consciousness confronts when
you awake in the morning and consider the
multiplicitous ways
that the day might progress.
That's chaos.
Chaos contains possibility.
And the question is, what attitude
should you embody to make the order
that's good or very good out
of the chaos of potential?
And the Genesis insistence is
that that's the pursuit of truth
aimed at love, right?
And that's the ultimate aim for the.
The forthright confrontation with
what's continually unexpected.
That's how you draw out of it.
What's the best? Imagine that one of my
security guys told me the other day a story.
He was in a rough part of San Diego.
I think the first day he worked for me, he
went into a convenience store and there's
a guy came up and tried
to rob him with a knife.
Now, my security guy isn't the kind of
guy that you can easily rob with a knife,
especially if you don't know.
What you're doing with the knife.
And he could tell that he didn't know
what he was doing with the knife.
So he laughed at him and
the guy burst into tears.
And my security guy took the knife and
then bought him a drink and a meal.
Right.
That's pretty good.
That's a high order example
of dealing with something.
What? Malevolent, chaotic,
radically unknown.
Right. That's a sign of mastery.
That. So there's a notion that because
human beings are made in the image of God,
that there's no upper
limit to their potential.
Christ tells his followers that they and
those who follow will do greater works than
he.
There's no obvious upper limit to
upward striving or to mastery.
And that means, in principle, that
there's no pit so deep that it can't be
confronted and
climbed out of or perhaps
transformed. Right.
That's the harrowing of hell in Christ's
three day journey through death and hell.
Right. The encounter with
what's radically abysmal.
Right. As a precondition for full life.
And it seems to me to be correct, because
I can't see how you could live fully
without having the courage to
confront death and malevolence.
You have to shy away.
Otherwise, you have to shy away
from anything that's deep.
You have to shy away from
anything that's frightening.
And then who knows how much development
you forego because of that?
Because maybe you didn't have to.
Right. Maybe you could have been
radically more than you are.
And so novelty, dragon and treasure.
Right. So that's part of what starts us
on our journey to enter the mythological
landscape, because I laid out the characters,
the pathways, the friends and the
foes, the agents of
magical transformation.
The difference between good and evil.
That puts us in the
mythological landscape.
The mythological landscape
describes the story.
It's the structure.
It's the underlying
structure of the story.
It highlights the fundamental
elements of every story.
Right. And the more the
deeper it is, the larger
number of stories that pattern undergirds.
Right. Because all great
stories have a pattern.
That's what makes them stories.
They wouldn't be stories if
they didn't have a pattern.
They wouldn't fit a category.
And the more fundamental
motifs are the root structure
of the plethora
of the largest number of stories, romance.
That's one category,
metacategory of story adventure.
That's another.
The proper admixture
is romantic adventure.
That's the story that
everyone wants to see.
Male and female alike.
An optimized, playful, romantic adventure.
Right. And that's the story that
imbues life with the maximal meaning.
Right.
Okay. So what happens when
something unexpected occurs?
When a rabbit hole appears?
How do you respond physiologically?
It's an anomaly. Right.
Which means it's something unexpected
isn't allowed to exist by the rules of the
game you're playing.
Right. Because if your
rules were complete,
everything that happened would be predictable
and you'd be on your way to your path.
So when an anomaly emerges, you either
have to restrategize or you have to
recalibrate your aim.
Okay. How do you do that?
Well, in a complex sequence, the
first reaction is emotional.
Right. And it's the
disinhibition of emotion.
So it's partly anxiety and
it's partly curiosity.
But it's more than that. It's like this.
It's like the opening of a floodgate of
potential emotional responses on the
positive side and the opening of a
floodgate of potential negative responses.
You can imagine that if something
particularly hair raising occurs,
a flood of possibilities go
through your mind. Right.
And so that's a journey through the
at hand possibilities of reaction
that are rising up from within you.
That's the.
Neurologically, if you're playing a game,
let's say there's a set of circuits, so to
speak, a network spirit that
inhibits all the competing games.
So you see this with athletes when
they're playing a high intensity game.
They can even break a limb and continue
playing because the motivational
significance of the proximal frame is so
intense that it just shuts everything else
down, even including pain.
Now, when they stop playing the game,
the pain will come roaring back.
But technically, it's inhibitory, which is
also why you're only focusing on a narrow
range of things instead of all the multitude
of things that you could be focusing
on. That's disinhibited, by the
way, with psychedelics, right?
Psychedelics remove that focal
frame and make everything relevant.
And everything is too much, far too much.
And normally does the same thing.
In fact, the neurochemical consequences of
psychedelics are an exaggeration of the
brain. The brain's response to anomaly.
It's the same thing.
It's a biochemically
induced stress response.
And stress renovelizes things.
Well, why?
Because what you were paying attention
to was wrong, or you wouldn't have
encountered something unknown.
So what should you pay attention to?
Who knows?
Something outside of what you
were paying attention to.
What's that?
That's a lot, right?
So that's overwhelming.
Now, it's also an entire
universe of new possibility.
But, well, that's the
dragon treasure conundrum.
How much possibility do you want?
You know, you see the specter of divorce
lurking behind every argument, right?
That's a bit more
possibility than you want.
Disinhibition of motivation and emotion
is the fundamental response to novelty.
So it's all the things you could do
come closer to hand.
So that's what anger does. Like, anger.
Anger. Anger primes you to react aggressively,
more rapidly or defensively, right?
Fear primes you to freeze or to run away.
When you don't know what's going on,
what should you be primed to do?
Everything.
Okay.
That's exciting in small doses,
especially if it's self administered.
But it's unbelievably
stressful in high doses.
In fact, that's a very good
definition of what stress is.
When you're stressed, it's because you're
preparing to do everything at once.
And to do that requires a tremendous
amount of psychophysiological effort.
And essentially what you do is you rob
your future stores of energy and resources
and burn them up in the present.
If you do that long enough, you die.
And so stress ages you, right?
And so this is another reason why
you want to keep your room clean.
You know, you want to keep everything
that you can in order, because if
something radically unexpected
occurs, maybe you'll get through it if there
aren't too many things clinging to you.
But if everything around you is in disarray
and maybe you contract some illness
that's quite severe,
maybe you could get through the
illness, you know, God willing.
But if it's the illness plus 100 other
things, it's like maybe that's the end of
you.
And so you prepare for the worst by
attempting to be pristine in your conduct.
And then your store of resilience is
greater.
And so it's good to take pains to
set things right and to address
the micro anomalies as they
arise so they don't aggregate.
So that's the rabbit hole.
That's the structure of
the rabbit hole, right?
You're trying to go from
point A to point B,
but there are things you don't understand
in the road, and the whole thing just goes
down the hole.
It isn't that you don't get to point B.
That's not the problem.
It's that the way you thought of point A
and the way you thought of point B
and everything you saw and all your
motivations and your emotions
were potentially wrong, right?
So it's not mere failure of strategy.
It's a failure of game and worse.
Or God, it can be worse than that because
the game you're playing might be dependent
on another game and underneath
that, yet another game.
Like the relationship you have with the
child is dependent on the integrity of your
marriage and the integrity
of your marriage is dependent on
your vow of chastity, let's say.
And so there are dependencies
in nested games.
And now and then you make
a mistake at a high level.
Something occurs at a high
level that stops that game,
but that indicates that something's
gone wrong way down at the bottom.
That's lipstick on the collar, right?
Which is, well, which is what?
That's the question, which is what?
The marriage game is over.
The future is completely different.
It's not what you envisioned.
The person you're married to, that isn't
the person you thought you were married to.
That means all your memories are wrong.
Going back how long?
Does that mean that your perception of
every person that you've ever been in love
with is wrong?
Is your whole perception of the
relationship between people wrong?
It's like in all those memories you
had of your past, how many of them are
wrong?
You wouldn't think the past
can change, but it can.
And so that's a black hole.
That can be a black hole.
And there's definitely a
dragon at the bottom of that.
So that's a descent into chaos,
right? So you can think about
tiers of emotional upset, right?
There's the emotional upset that
necessitates a small course correction.
That's just a minor
annoyance, petty annoyance.
There's the upset
that forces you to reconstitute the game.
There's an upset that forces you to evaluate
the hierarchical structure of all your
games and to see where the error occurred.
That's a rough one, right?
That's a life changing transformation.
Assuming you live through it.
Much more likely to live through it if
you've explored the depths voluntarily to
begin with.
Right? So you're not caught unaware.
Down the rabbit hole.
So, you know, the Taoists believe
that the world is made out of
order and chaos, right?
Yin and Yang.
Why? Because that's what
the world is made out of.
Places you can predict.
Places where things occur as you expect.
Places where the game you're
playing remains valid.
And the place you are when
all of that disappears.
Right? And what's that chaos?
Well, it's terrifying.
It's unstructured.
It's potent.
It's potential. It's raw potential.
It's everything the world
is that you don't know.
It's all the things you could be
if you were other than you were.
And that's chaos.
And that's the landscape of
possibility that the Spirit of God
extracts the world of order from.
Not only at the beginning of time,
but at the beginning of all things.
Always.
Right? That's the beginning of things.
The encounter. The
encounter with what's new.
The exploration of that
realm of possibility.
The adoption of an attitude towards it.
And then the casting of it
into predictable order.
And you do that every
time you do something.
You do that at a micro level
every time you move your eyes.
So, and when something goes involuntarily
wrong, it's down the rabbit hole
into the realm of chaos.
Right? That's what a
baptism is, by the way.
Except it's done voluntarily.
That's a return to the
pre-cosmogonic chaos.
Right? That's a radical renewal
and a return to the beginning.
That's how everything
is revitalized always.
And the question again to bring this issue
up is, what's the nature of the attitude
that best enables you
to prevail when faced
with the cataclysm and the
opportunity to recast chaotic,
chaotic possibility into order?
Right.